Guide to the Jimmy Don Smith collection, 1965-1990 MS 994
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jimmy Don Smith collection
1965-1990
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Smith, Rutherene
MS 994
2.25 Linear Feet (1 LP box and 1 oversize box)
This collection contains audio, photographs, posters, and other materials related to the music career of Jimmy Don Smith.
Biographical / Historical
James Donald Smith who went by the performance name Jimmy Don Smith was born in Fort Worth, TX on October 28, 1948. He attended Oklahoma State University. At 19, Smith, a self-taught musician, moved to Houston and began a career as a lead guitarist and singer. He joined a variety of bands including Blackwell, The Boontz All-Stars, The Rhythm Tramps, and his last band The Cold Cuts or Jimmy Don Smith and the Cold Cuts. He recorded at least three albums with Blackwell, The Boontz All-Stars, and The Cold Cuts.
In 1985, Smith was diagnosed with cancer and passed on January 25, 1986. His widow, Rutherene Smith aka Ruth Cole Hammett Smith raised money and endowed the Jimmy Don Smith Memorial Scholarship at the University of St. Thomas in Houston.
Content Description
This collection contains audio, photographs, posters, and other materials related to the music career of Jimmy Don Smith.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rutherene Smith aka Ruth Cole Hammett Smith in 2021.
Related Materials
Session recording located in the Roger Francis "Rock" Romano collection, MS 908.
Index Terms
Subjects
Rock music; Blues (Music) -- Texas -- Houston; Blues (Music); Music
Subjects (Persons)
Smith, Rutherene
- Series I: General files
  - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fliers, 1972-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jimmy Don Smith Memorial Scholarship, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1970-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Press materials, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Photographs, proofs, scrapbook
  - Bands with Jimmy Don Smith, 1965-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jimmy Don Smith by himself, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jimmy Don Smith with Muddy Waters, 1981-09-20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bands and individuals not including Jimmy Don Smith, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Page proofs and negatives, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rutherene Smith, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Bloontz All-Stars scrapbook, 1972 (Box 1)
- Series III: Audio
  - Sub-Series A: LPs
    - Blackwell - self-titled, 1970 (Box 1)
    - The Cold Cuts - "Meat the Cold Cuts!", 1982 (Box 1)
  - Sub-Series B: CDs
    - Jimmy Don Smith and the Cold Cuts - Blossoms (2) (Box 1)
    - Jimmy Don smith and the Cold Cuts - Baton Rouge Doyle (Box 1)
    - Jimmy Don Smith and the Cold Cuts - Live in Baton Rouge (Box 1)
    - Jimmy Don Smith and the Cold Cuts - Big Meat Beat - Live in Baton Rouge (Box 1)
    - Cold Cuts at Chief's Baton Rouge, 1981-01-16 (Box 1)
    - Cold Cuts (Box 1)
    - Cold Cuts - Houston 3 piece (Box 1)
- Series IV: Oversize materials
  - Ephemera, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Posters featuring Jimmy Don Smith, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Notable posters include:
    Willie Dixon and the Chicago All-Stars, ZZ Top, Bloontz All-Star Band at Liberty Hall - 1971-05-06 - 1971-05-09 Muddy Waters, The Cold Cuts at Tipitina's, 1981-09-20 Junkin Bone with Bloontz All-Star Band at Liberty Hall, 1971
  - Posters not featuring Jimmy Don Smith, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    The Lonnie Brooks Band, ca. 1980 - signed Freddie King and Storm at Liberty Hall, 1971-08-27 - 1971-08-28 Clifton Chenier at Fitzgerald's, 1983-09-30 - signed Townes Van Zandt at Fitzgerald's, 1980-09-12 - 1980-09-13 - signed Albert King at Fitzgerald's, 1982-11-18 - signed B. B. King at Rockefeller's, 1985-02-13 - 1985-02-16 - signed
  - Bell-bottom jeans with patches (2), 1971 (Box 2)